If you dug a hole straight into Saturn,
the first thing you'd feel is there's
not much that's solid. If you look at a
cross-section of the planet, this much
of it is gas and liquid. So, first you'd
be diving through this frigid atmosphere
of helium and hydrogen with icy ammonia
clouds. And it's got winds that are
about four times faster than the
strongest hurricane winds on Earth.
Then, at about 2,000 km down, you plunge
into a liquid hydrogen layer. Here, the
pressure is thousands of times what it
is on the surface of Earth. So hydrogen
gas is squished into a liquid. But you
dive further and you reach another
liquid layer made of metallic hydrogen.
Here the pressure is even greater. Now
the liquid hydrogen acts like a thick
metal soup that can conduct electricity.
This is where Saturn's powerful magnetic
field is created. It's nearly 600 times
more powerful than Earth's. And finally,
you reach the core. Scientists still
debate how big it is exactly, but new
research suggests it's a slushy ball of
ice and rock and gas. Subscribe.